You may wonder:
if surgery physically removes the cancer
from the body,
and systemic therapies also go throughout
the body to target the cancer cells,
Why is radiation necessary?
Radiation plays an important role
either alone
or in partnership
with these other treatment methods.
Surgery and Radiation Therapy
Some tumors are localized to one
area of the body, and surgery
can be effective in removing the tumor.
However, surgeons are only able
to take out the bulk of the tumor
that they can see or that is safe
to remove without harming other organs.
As a result,
there may be cells left over in the body
that the surgeons could not see
and thus could not completely remove.
Radiation to the surgical bed
after surgery,
helps to target any remaining cells
so that those leftover
cancer cells
do not continue to grow and divide.
One analogy that may be helpful is this:
surgery is like physically pulling weeds
out of your garden,
and radiation is like spraying weedkiller
in the patches of soil
after to prevent
the growth of further weeds.
Systemic Treatments and Radiation Therapy
With systemic treatments,
radiation can work
synergistically with these agents
to make the chemo or immunotherapy
even more powerful.
This is dependent on the type of cancer
you have and its molecular markers,
and the exact recipe of treatment
may vary from person to person,
tailored to your specific situation.
Your radiation oncologist and medical
oncologist will work together to determine
if and when both agents are appropriate
for you.
Some individuals get chemotherapy
before they have radiation.
at the same time as radiation
And others get chemotherapy
after finishing the course of radiation.
Often in head and neck cancers,
chemotherapy can be used to enhance
the effect of radiation.
What we call
radiosensitizing chemotherapy.